<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief historical relation of the empire of Russia, and of its original growth out of 24 great dukedomes, into one entire empire, since the yeer 1514. Humbly presented to the view and serious perusal of all true-hearted English-men, that love and honour the peace and happiness of this their native country. / By J.F.</title>
            <author>J. F.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85072</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F28</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1485_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22889</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871857</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871857</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170021</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85072)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170021)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 190:E1485[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief historical relation of the empire of Russia, and of its original growth out of 24 great dukedomes, into one entire empire, since the yeer 1514. Humbly presented to the view and serious perusal of all true-hearted English-men, that love and honour the peace and happiness of this their native country. / By J.F.</title>
                  <author>J. F.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 44, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for William Larnar, at the Blackmoore head neer Fleet-bridge.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept. 5.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Russia --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170021:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A brief Hiſtorical RELATION Of the Empire of RUSSIA, AND Of its Original Growth OUT OF 24 <hi>Great Dukedomes,</hi> INTO <hi>One entire Empire,</hi> Since the yeer 1514.</p>
            <p>Humbly preſented to the view and ſerious peruſal of all true-hearted Engliſh-men, that love and honour the peace and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of this their native Country.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.C.</hi> for <hi>William</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, at the Blackmoors head neer Fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ge. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170021:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170021:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He clear Fountain of pure Juſtice, Judgement, and Mercy, ſpringing forth in its clear and free cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, to all degrees of men without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, is that which truely advances a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, brings glory to God, peace to the mindes of a diſtempered people, and true honour and ſafety to the Supreme Ruler, who thereby becomes embraced by all in the arms of Love, and born upon their hands of Saſety, and moſt freely on all occaſions ſupplied with their gifts of bounty.</p>
            <p>The impartial obſervation and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of this, by <hi>Borice</hi> the Elected Emperour of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> made him ſo famous, and ingraved him ſo deep in the hearty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of all the people, as that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb facs="tcp:170021:3"/>themſelves more happie and ſafe in him, then in him or them whoſe right by birth at that time the Empire was; <hi>as in the following Story will appear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the impregnable Staff of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercie,</hi> by which like a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd he led the people, and by which, like a most valiant Champion, he quell'd and beat down to the ground all his enemies, and all that ever dared in the leaſt to oppoſe or appear againſt him. It was That, that became a Wall of Peace and Safety to him, and an unexpreſsible hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to that Nation, during the whole time of his happie Reign.</p>
            <p>This happineſs from my ſoul I wiſh and deſire may ever attend him, whom God hath at preſent placed over us, and by whom, as by a <hi>ſecond Joſhua,</hi> the Lord hath done great things, and hath brought mighty things to paſs for us; yea, ſuch, as all our Chronicles, and all the Stories of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> cannot parallel.</p>
            <p>For which ſelect Inſtrument, duty bindes us to return glory and praiſe to
<pb facs="tcp:170021:3"/>God, and to beg, that the Lord in mercy to this Nation would keep his heart cloſe to himſelf, cauſing him to walk cloſe to the Lord by the impartial Rules of <hi>Juſtice, Judgement,</hi> and <hi>Mercy:</hi> knowing in ſome meaſure, by his own expreſsions, that it is the deſire of his ſoul ſo to do; even to walk cloſe with the Lord, and humbly with his God.</p>
            <p>But methinks I hear ſome Christians ſay, <hi>That they dare not approve of theſe high Titles of Honour to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed, ſeeing they do not reap the fruits of Liberty and Juſtice accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Reformation promiſe, for that they ſtill ſee Iniquity, Bondage, and Oppreſſion, to bear the ſway; the dens of Cruelty upheld; the Law ſtreaming forth in as corrupt a dela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory chargeable current as before; the Adverſaries encouraged, and his and this Nations true Friends ſlighted.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170021:4"/>
            <p>My anſwer and humble Chriſtian de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to all ſuch ſhall be onely this, That they would be pleaſed to poſſeſs their ſouls in patience: wait upon the Lord, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs are long their eyes ſhall ſee and behold the ſalvation of God, deliverance wrought, yea mighty things brought to paſs by him, (ſeeing new the Lord hath been pleaſed to put the power into his hand.) For it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into my heart to think or believe, that ever his Highneſs, for whom the Lord hath done ſo great things, (and if this be not enough, will yet do greater things) ſhould ſo far diſhonour God, and himſelf, and all that have taken part with him, (by putting their hand unto the Work) as to ſuffer theſe <hi>Norman</hi> evils to continue; or that ever he ſhould fall off from the pious Rules of Juſtice, Charity, and Love, ſo far, as to ſlight thoſe his friends, who have ever been faithful to him, and this their native Country, and have ſuffered for him. Surely, Grace and Goodneſs teacheth him, who is in mercy ſanctified therewith, far better things; and will
<pb facs="tcp:170021:4"/>enable him to bring this to paſs, and much more, mangre all his and this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions enemies. Therefore let us not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, lest we be found fighting againſt God: and let him but keep cloſe unto the Lord his God, and then go on and proſper. I ſay as I ſaid long before, Go on, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper.</p>
            <p>Now the God of all grace, mercy, and peace, who hath bound up his life in the bundle of his grace, ſanctifie him thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out by his holy Spirit, perfect his work by him, and by him make bare the arm of his mighty power for us, againſt all the potent enemies of this Nation, who threaten his and our deſtruction, and this Nation's ruine; and cauſe his Highneſs ſtill to be the Lord's powerful victorious threſhing-inſtrument upon his and this Nations enemies, as alſo the Lords hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie inſtrument of juſtice and mercy to the people of God, and to all the poor, diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, oppreſſed, and enſlaved; to the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, the fatherleſs, and ſtrangers, in this
<pb facs="tcp:170021:5"/>Land; that ſo his fame may ring thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world, and his name become as a ſweet odour in the noſtrils of all men.</p>
            <p>All which are, and ever ſhall be, the conſtant addreſſes to the throne of grace in that behalf, for him, and the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hearty deſires of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>His Highneſs and this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths moſt humble and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervant in the Lord, during life,
J. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170021:5"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most honorable, and Truely honored, and Beloved in the Lord Jeſus:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord having cauſed me, in the days of this my Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, even from my youth up, to taſte both of ſweet and bitter waters, to partake in forraign and domeſtick Princes Courts, abundance of Proſperity, and in my own Country the like meaſure of bitter Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, for theſe fourteen or fifteen yeers paſt.</p>
            <p>In which my days of travel, and reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence at home ſome part of the Raign of the two late Kings of <hi>England,</hi> I was dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to note and obſerve the moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able paſſages preſenting themſelves to my Genius, and in ſpecial ſome, which happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the vaſt and potent Empire of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> (to ſome of which paſſages I was an eye-witneſs.)</p>
            <p>Of which, as alſo of the original riſe and growth of thoſe people of <hi>Ruſſia</hi> to one
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170021:6"/>entire Empire, I have been often, for many yeers paſt, by many ſollicited to make ſome brief deſcription or relation. In anſwer therefore now to their earneſt deſires, and according to my beſt intelligence, I have adventured to ſet pen to paper, for their further ſatisfaction, in brief, as followeth.</p>
            <p>The people now called <hi>Ruſſians,</hi> or <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covites,</hi> are ſaid to be originally deſcended from the ancient <hi>Scythians;</hi> and thoſe of them now called <hi>Beloruſians,</hi> are ſaid to be deſcended from the <hi>Ruthenians,</hi> whoſe chief City then was <hi>Navagradia;</hi> and the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians</hi> principal City was then called <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodeemer;</hi> who upon the incurſions made by <hi>Tamerlain</hi> the great Cham of the <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> into thoſe ſeveral parts, many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of them were ſcattered or ſown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into the remoteſt parts, and clodeſt climates of that vaſt Continent, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon intituled themſelves <hi>Ros-ſeyans,</hi> which ſignifieth, A people ſown abroad upon the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>The people, in proceſs of time, divided themſelves into four and twenty ſeveral Dukedoms; and ſo continued, until the yeer 1514.</p>
            <p>At which time, <hi>John Bazilious Chercaskee</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170021:6"/>the then-Duke of <hi>Volodeemer,</hi> moſt ſubtilly contrived and raiſed a diſcord amongſt all the Dukes of <hi>Ruſſia;</hi> by means whereof, they having weakned and deſtroyed one another, the ſaid <hi>John Bazilious</hi> within ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few yeers gained the Conqueſt of them all, together with the Kingdoms of <hi>Cazan, Aſtrachan, Chorelia,</hi> and <hi>Sibiria;</hi> and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them into one entire Empire, he was in the yeer 1524 declared and crowned Emperour of <hi>Ruſſa,</hi> placing his Imperial Throne in the City of <hi>Moſco,</hi> the then-chief City of the Dukedom of <hi>Moſcovia;</hi> where it remaineth to this day.</p>
            <p>In his days, the Cham of the grim <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> invaded <hi>Ruſſa</hi> with an Army of Four hundred thouſand men, beſieged the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial City of <hi>Moſco</hi> ſome three months, burnt and ſpoiled all the Country many hundred miles in compaſs; and upon his departure, he required Homage of the Emperour; which was, That the Emperor of <hi>Ruſſia</hi> ſhould come forth of the City of <hi>Moſco</hi> on foot, attended by his Princes and Nobles of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> bare-headed; and that the Emperour ſhould then bring Oats in his Cap, and preſent them to the Cham of <hi>Tartary</hi> his horſe, (he himſelf then ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon his horſe-back) and to feed the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170021:7"/>horſe out of his Cap: All which, for the ſaving of the lives of many thouſands of his people, and utter devaſtation of his Empire, the Emperour performed, feeding the great Cham of <hi>Tartary</hi>'s horſe with Oats out of his own Cap, or Colpack.</p>
            <p>This Homage being performed, the Cham of <hi>Tartary</hi> ſtroaked the Emperour of <hi>Ruſſia</hi> three times on the face and beard, preſented him with a Cymiter, and a Bowe and Caſe of Arrows, and ſo depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, carrying many thouſands captive.</p>
            <p>This <hi>John Bazilious</hi> the Emperour, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his latter days, grew a mighty Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, delighting much in blood, cauſing many of his Nobles (on the leaſt occaſion) to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> themſelves upon their own ſwords, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thrown alive unto Bears, Wolves, and Lions: ſome he cauſed (both men and women) to be tyed to ſpits, and roſted alive, till they died; ſome to be torn aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by horſes: and many other unexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible inhumane cruelties were by him pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed; who, after he had (like a ſecond <hi>Herod</hi>) reigned 35 yeers, (being very aged) he died of a Dropſie; at which time there was a Note of the names of ſeventeen per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons under his pillow,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A Note ſound of</hi> 17 <hi>perſons by him appointed for death.</hi>
               </note> appointed to die.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170021:7"/>
            <p>To him ſucceeded his ſon <hi>Theodor,</hi> who being of a ſhallow capacity, and from his youth addicted to blinde devotion, and ringing of bells, did thereby neglect the great affairs of the Empire, whereby the people, though acquitted from his father the Tyrant, yet their burthens of Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Oppreſſion by his folly increaſed. They then, by and upon their humble Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the Emperour, and by his conſent and permiſſion, choſe the then-Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Imperial Army, <hi>(Borice Feodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowick Godoonove)</hi> Lord Protector of the Empire; who (though illiterate) was a man endowed with many excellent natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts, being of a deep judgement, a ſtrong memory, and of a diſcerning ſpirit, endowed with much ſageneſs; being alſo a great lover of Juſtice: the laſt of theſe, crowned all the reſt of his vertues, raiſing him high in the hearty affections of the people, ſo that to this day his fame rings thorow all that vaſt Empire, (like that of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in this Nation.)</p>
            <p>By him were all their exorbitant abuſes of their Law regulated, and brought to their priſtine condition: all the Provincial Vayvodes and Chancellors were (for acts of injuſtice and oppreſſion) ſeverely puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170021:8"/>in their perſons, and by their eſtates compelled to yeeld ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to all parties by them wronged by falſe Judgement.
<note place="margin">Note this well.</note> The long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſurped power of all the Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Prieſts and Friers, in Secular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, quite extinguiſhed. And by fear and terrour of puniſhment without reſpect of perſons, Juſtice in its purity was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled from the corrupteſt perſons in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; which forced alſo the greateſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory perſons formerly in power, to vail and crouch before the Lord Protector, ſeeing the peoples affections thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as a wall of braſs for his ſafety and preſervation from their ſecret plottings of his deſtruction, (by ſhooting their ſecret arrows of detraction abroad, to his defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) for which, many of them, not long after, by his impartial hand of Juſtice were made exemplary.</p>
            <p>Thus, after the Emperour <hi>Theodor</hi> had poſſeſſed the Imperial Diademe 15 yeers, he died in the Imperial Palace at <hi>Moſco,</hi> 1566. At which time, the Lord Protector <hi>Borice</hi> retiring to the Maiden Monaſtery, ſeemed to reſolve the leading of a Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick life, and to wave the Government of that great Empire; which occaſioned his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170021:8"/>ſecret enemies (though before, ſeeming friends) to diſplay their Banners of revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſpeeches againſt him, endeavouring both by themſelves and their inſtruments to render him odious to the people. Yea, many of his own ſervants appeared then in their colours; which afterwards cauſed many of their heads to cleave to the block.</p>
            <p>For, the Souldiery, over whom he ſtill remained as Lord General during the time of his Protectorſhip, and the Commonalty (whoſe affections he had gained by acts of Juſtice and Mercy, exerciſed by him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear or flattery) did all unanimouſly make their repair to him to the ſaid Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Monaſtery, and there openly declaring his Paternal care, and prudential diſpoſing of the affairs of that vaſt Empire, with all the ſeveral conquered parts thereof, in the days of their late Emperour <hi>Theodor Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowiche,</hi> did preſs upon him the acceptance of the Imperial Diademe. Upon whoſe acceptation, they forthwith declared him for their Emperour: and ſoon after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to the Imperial Palace, he was with very great magnificence and acclamation of the people, crowned Emperour of <hi>Ruſſia;</hi> being a Gentleman of an humble ſpirit,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170021:9"/>conſtant in his reſolutions, and carried al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways an open ear to the complaints of all poor and oppreſſed perſons, doing them ſpeedy juſtice. His cuſtom was to ſit three days in the fore-noons with his Privie Councel, and in the afternoons to hear and anſwer Petitions; cauſing his Orders and References always to be drawn up in his own preſence; puniſhing all Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors and other Officers for their corrupt and partial dealing, and for their ſlighting of his Decrees, and falſifying of his Orders and References.</p>
            <p>He alſo called all the Provincial Judges and Chancellors to a ſtrict account yeerly, and moſt impartially heard all mens com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt them: and ſuch as were found corrupt and faulty, he puniſhed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely in their perſons, and by their eſtates compelled them to give full ſatisfaction to all perſons by them wronged in Judgment, or any ways oppreſſed or defrauded.</p>
            <p>He carried alſo a vigilant eye over all the Lords of his Privie Councel; ſo that none of them durſt tread out of the path of Impartial Juſtice, either for reward, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or affection, to any of their neereſt allies, or deareſt friends.</p>
            <p>He alſo ordered the determination of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170021:9"/>all Controverſies and Suits in Law to be within 40 days; and the charges of a Suit in Law not to exceed a <hi>Greevna,</hi> which is 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> Engliſh: <hi>viz.</hi> 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> for the Citation, 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> for the Warrant, and 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> for a copie of the Decretal Order.</p>
            <p>And for any one that had commenced a falſe and vexatious Suit againſt any, he was to pay treble damages,
<note place="margin">Pure Juſtice.</note> and to ſuffer the like puniſhment which he intended thereby to have inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the perſon by him unjuſtly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O what happineſs, what peace, what concord, would ſuch a courſe of Juſtice produce here in</hi> England.</p>
            <p>And for the ſale of houſes and lands of Inheritance, he ordained a book to be kept in every Province, called, <hi>The everlaſting book,</hi> (or, as here in <hi>England</hi> it was called formerly, when the practice of the Law ran in its pure current, <hi>The Dooms day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book</hi>) which is there continued to this preſent. By which means, all vexatious Suits, unjuſt Claims, and all Frauds, are prevented. The people there, cannot mortgage nor ſell their Land, Houſes, nor Leaſes, two or three times over, to ſeveral perſons; as uſually here in <hi>England:</hi> nor
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170021:10"/>is any there cheated of their Patrimonies, nor conſtrained to ſell or mortgage their lands or goods, or both, to maintain a long and tedious Suit in Law, by giving content to their inſatiable Cormorant-Lawyers, Attorneys, Sollicitors, as we do here in <hi>England;</hi> where the recovery of a debt of 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> hath coſt ſome men above 200 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> in Law. Yea, ſome thouſands of families have been ruined in defence of their rights, by the preſent abuſive practiſe of the Law.</p>
            <p>Neither have they there (nor in any Country under the whole heavens, but in cruel <hi>England</hi>) any murthering dens and dungeons of cruelty for impriſoning men and women for debt, till they ſtarve and die in priſon: (contrary to our own ancient Statutes yet in force. See the book inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>Liberty vindicated againſt Slavery, fol.</hi> 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. chap. 4. 21 <hi>Edw.</hi> 2. D. 172. 13 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. B. 153. 8 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. chap. 18, 20. 34 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. chap. 4. 23 <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. chap. 10. <hi>Magna Chart.</hi> chap. 35. <hi>Westm.</hi> 1. ch. 26.3 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. ch. 26.25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. chap. 4.</p>
            <p>Nor is there, any arreſted nor impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon frivolous, falſe, and vexatious A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, unjuſt Orders, Reports and Decrees
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170021:10"/>daily, as they are here in <hi>England.</hi> Nor is there any ſuch Horſe-leeches to ſuck the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal blood of men and women committed to their cuſtody into Gaols and Priſons, as we have here. For all which unexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible cruelties, doubtleſs the wrath and vengeance of God will ere long fall heavie upon the Nation, if not remedied, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſeveral Vows, Proteſtations, Declarations, and Manifeſto's, made to God and this Nation many yeers ſince, both by Parliament and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rmy.</p>
            <p>In this moſt noble, juſt, and famous Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours days, the cruel, the mighty, nor the oppreſſing Miſer, durſt not wrong nor op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the poor, the widow, the fatherleſs, nor the ſtranger. The Judges and Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors durſt not ſtep aſide our of the ſtrait path of Juſtice, for money, favour, nor affection: witneſs that exemplary juſt Sentence of his paſſed on the Chancellor of the Province of <hi>Rezane,</hi> who for 100 Robles bribe, (which is 50 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr>) had moſt unjuſtly decreed a poor widows Land of Inheritance from her: whereof proof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by her made to the Emperour, the Lord Chancellors was by him degraded, and ſentenced to have the like bag of money hang'd about his neck, and to be whipped
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170021:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170021:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170021:12"/>by the common Hang-man, from the great Chancery-Office to the Market-place, and back to the ſaid Office; there the money to be melted, and poured down his throat. All which was done accordingly.</p>
            <p>O if this pure Juſtice and Mercy were exerciſed here in <hi>England,</hi> how unexpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly would it elevate his Highneſs in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of all the people, and engrave him in their hearts! whereby he would then become like to the famous Queen <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi> who upon any motion abroad from her Palace, had many thouſands at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending on the high-ways to congratulate her with their loyalty, and loud acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſent up to heaven for her Majeſties long life, health, and proſperity.</p>
            <p>In her days there is ſaid to be but one Serjeant at Law, at the Common-Pleas bar, (called, Serjeant <hi>Benlowes</hi>) who was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to plead both for the Plaintiff and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant; for which he was to take ten Groats of each party, and no more: and to manifeſt his impartial dealing to both parties, he was therefore to wear a party-coloured garment, and to have on his head a black Cap of impartial Juſtice, and under it a white linen Coyf of Innocencie. All which was in the days of King <hi>James,</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170021:12"/>to Injuſtice, Oppreſſion, and Bribery. Serjeants were by him made in abundance; and a Serjeants place was then ſold for 800 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> but in the days of the late King, the price of Iniquity was raiſed to 1500 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> who at one time made thirteen Serjeants at Law.</p>
            <p>I will wade no further into this ſea of Wickedneſs, leſt ſome of the old ſtamp, and long Robe, ſhould finde themſelves agrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but reſolve to return to the matter in hand.</p>
            <p>The like puniſhment was by this famous Emperour moſt juſtly inflicted upon the Great Lord Chancellor of <hi>Moſco;</hi> who for paſſing an unjuſt Decree, was degraded and whipped, and had thirty laſhes, by the common Hang-man, upon the <hi>Cozoel,</hi> or wooden Gate, before his own Office.</p>
            <p>The like was by him inflicted on the Vayvode or Governour of <hi>Vaſema,</hi> who for injuſtice and oppreſſion was alſo whipped, and his eſtate decreed to ſatisfie the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by him wronged.</p>
            <p>I would inſtance many more the like acts of Juſtice which flowed from that truely-magnanimous Prince; as alſo, how the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til deceitful knot of a number of grand oppreſſors was by him broken; who by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170021:13"/>their ſubtil contrivances, in and by their accuſtomed corrupt practices, in and by their Law, had enſlaved the Nation to their corrupt wills, and ruined thouſands of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies: But I hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that little that hath been related, is ſufficient for any to take conſideration of, and to make it their own moſt honourable practical example; to the glory of God, the good of this Nation, and their own eternal honour.</p>
            <p>And thus after the poor oppreſſed man's Patriot, even this famous Emperour, had happily reigned 36 yeers, he departed this life: whoſe death was much lamented by all the people for many yeers: to whom ſucceeded his ſon <hi>Theodore,</hi> who being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 17 yeers old, reigned but ſix months.</p>
            <p>In whoſe time, one <hi>Demetrius</hi> (who from his youth being brought up in the Free-School of <hi>Warſovia</hi> in <hi>Poland</hi>) gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out, and was credibly ſaid to be the ſon of <hi>John Bazilious</hi> the firſt Emperour; who having married <hi>Marinca</hi> the eldeſt daughter of <hi>Sandomerskee,</hi> one of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of <hi>Poland,</hi> was by <hi>Sigiſmundus</hi> King of <hi>Poland</hi> ſupplied with 20000 horſe; who thereupon entred this great Empire of <hi>Ruſſia</hi> with an Army of 240000 horſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred with the Emperours great Hoſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170021:13"/>conſiſting of 50000 horſe and 150000 foot, and after four ſeveral ſet Battels, he overthrew this great Imperial Hoſt, march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to the Imperial City, and after Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons (cauſing the young Emperour <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor</hi> to be ſtrangled) he entred the City; and being forthwith crowned <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or Emperour, he poſſeſſed the Imperial Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme 28 months.</p>
            <p>He was a Gentleman very comely of perſonage, active of body, and a great Scholar, highly affecting the Engliſh, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and Polonian Nations; being alſo himſelf, for his valour and generoſity of ſpirit, greatly beloved of all his victorious Army. But coming to poſſeſs the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Throne, and the glory thereof, he gave himſelf up to all maner of delightful pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes, referring the management of all State-affairs to his Privie Councel: and being wholly led by his chief Secretary <hi>Panne Boochinskee,</hi> he confined his ear to the ſaid <hi>Boochinskee,</hi> and ſome other few Polonian Flatterers and Paraſites about him; receiving alſo into favour ſome of the Ruſſian Nobility, and conferring places of Honour and Truſt upon them, hoping thereby to win and endear them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; who notwithſtanding became as ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170021:14"/>Serpents in his boſome, and proved the fatal inſtruments of his ruine.</p>
            <p>But that which proved moſt advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to his enemies, and fatal to himſelf, was, his not admitting any into his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, (as that famous Emperour <hi>Borice</hi> with all freeneſs uſed to do) but ſuch onely as thoſe Paraſites and Flatterers pleaſed to admit, for affection, favor, or reward; &amp; ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his ears againſt the cries of the poor oppreſſed Petitioners, he neglected to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer their Petitions: whereby, the hearts of the people were exaſperated againſt him. The reins of injuſtice, tyranny &amp; oppreſſion were let looſe to all oppreſſors; the Lords of his Councel acted by the Rule of their own wills; his Secretary <hi>Boochinskee</hi> became lawleſs and graceleſs: none durſt prefer a complaint againſt him. Every one of theſe his Flatterers made hay for themſelves, whilſt the proſperous ſunſhine of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Imperial favour diſplayed his rayes upon them, without any real affection, or conſcientious care in them for his Majeſties honour and ſafety: the fruit whereof pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, not long after, to be the fatal loſs of their own lives, and great eſtates ſo impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly gained.</p>
            <p>For, the irreconcileable old Imperial
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170021:14"/>ſubtil Nobility, Gentry, Chancellors, and Clergie, having ingratiated themſelvs with him, did by their inſtruments (at a diſtance inceſſantly in ſecret) render the Emperour odious to the people, and guilty of all thoſe grievous burthens of Injuſtice and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, which by their own unjuſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotted practices they had laid upon the people; whereby they moſt ſubtilly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed their diabolical end, which was, the untimely deſtruction of his Royal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by the cruel hands of <hi>Baſilius Shuskee,</hi> one of the reconciled Nobility, who not long before, for ſome treacherous practice, had his head upon the Block; yet the Emperour in his clemencie pardoned him: who not long after, through the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of ſome of the Ruſſian Lords, was made Privie Councellor, whereby he was the better enabled to compaſs his reſolved barbarous deſigne, which was, the cruel deſtruction of the Emperours perſon, and of the lives of all his victorious Army, conſiſting then of 25000 valiant men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Polonian, Germane, and Hungarian Horſe, who were all of them maſſacred the ſame day, and their houſes rifled; their wives and children expoſed to miſery, and very many of them cruelly butchered by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170021:15"/>the rude multitude within the City of <hi>Moſco:</hi> which inhumane act cauſed a Sea of blood to have its current thorow many of the ſtreets within the ſaid City.</p>
            <p>Thus the glory of this victorious He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick ſpirit, was extinguiſhed in one day: and all that truely adhered unto him, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered with him, both in their eſtates and lives, about the 20 of <hi>May,</hi> 1604.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bazilius</hi> having thus butchered this gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Prince, and removed all obſtacles, by deſtroying the Army, he was proclaimed Emperour of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> (by <hi>Mighayla Scopeene</hi> General of the Ruſſian Army) and ſpeedily after, crowned: who being ſcarce warm in the Imperial Throne, began forthwith to diſplay the Banner of Tyranny, in reſtoring the covetous Clergie to their former pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and juriſdiction in Secular affairs; and moſt perfidiouſly, contrary to his oath and promiſe made to the people at the time of his election, he looſed the reins of injuſtice and oppreſſion to all the Vayvodes and Provincial Chancellors, and began to lay great Taxes on the people; and, like <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the third of <hi>England,</hi> he beheaded ſome who were the primary inſtruments of placing the Imperial Diademe on his head, cauſing alſo <hi>Mighaylo Scopeene</hi> the General
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170021:15"/>of the Imperial Army to be ſecretly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by poyſon. Which acts of his, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him odious to all degrees of men, exaſperated the ſpirits of the Nobility a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and alienated the hearts of all the people from him; and chiefly, for that their grievances were not heard, nor their burthens of oppreſſion taken off, in all the ſix yeers time of his Reign; which at length emboldened the Nobility and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the City, with a reſolute ſpirit, to lay hold of him, (wherein a Citizen, one <hi>Theodor Andronave</hi> was a prime actor) who gagg'd him, bound him fast in a Sled, and ſent him poſt priſoner unto <hi>Sigiſmundus</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> laying to his charge the murthering of their late Emperour <hi>Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius:</hi> who being arrived at <hi>Warſovia</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> he was ordered to ſafe cuſtody, where he ended his days moſt miſerably, in the yeer of Chriſt 1610.</p>
            <p>The Nobility and flattering Clergie forthwith proceed in electing <hi>Uladiſlaus,</hi> the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s eldeſt ſon, for their Emperour; who thereupon ſent one <hi>Panne Zoltefskee</hi> with 10000 Horſe, to take and keep poſſeſſion for him: upon whoſe arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val into the Imperial City of <hi>Moſco,</hi> the Citizens made ſome oppoſition; but were
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170021:16"/>ſoon appeaſed by the Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. The Poliſh General thereupon gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a greater ſtrength into the City, which cauſed ſeveral tumults; the Lords there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon cauſed all the Citizens to be diſarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and but one hatchet left to every three houſes to cleave their wood: which act did mightily enrage the Citizens againſt the Lords and Polonians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zoltefskee</hi> well weighing the power of the Citizens, and weakneſs of his Army to keep poſſeſſion of ſo vaſt a City, did thereupon adminiſter an Oath of Loyalty to all his Souldiery, commanding them on the ſixth day of the then-month of <hi>May,</hi> every one at one of the clock in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fire their lodgings, and not to ſpare man, woman, nor childe: which was done accordingly, and above 130000 perſons maſſacred, beſides thoſe that were burnt in their beds and houſes.</p>
            <p>Thus the buildings of that famous City (ſaid then to be 26 miles in compaſs) were all turned into aſhes in one day, except the three ſtone-walls environing each other at a very great diſtance, and the Emperours Palace, with ſome Monaſteries, and other buildings of ſtone: but the fourth wall, which environed all the reſt, together with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170021:16"/>the ſuburbs without that wall, reaching a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove three miles in length, were all burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the wall being all of maſſie timber, and earth.</p>
            <p>But the unſavoury fruit of this their bloody Tragedie, was by the juſt hand of heaven returned into their own boſomes: for, the Country forthwith raiſed two mighty Armies under the conduct of the Lord <hi>Troobetſcoy</hi> and the Lord <hi>Pazarskee,</hi> who beſieged the Polonians in the City, cloſe on every ſide, for the ſpace of two yeers; and, through extreme famine, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced the Polonians to yeeld up that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Metropolitan City, and therewith the Prince of <hi>Poland</hi>'s right to the Empire of <hi>Ruſſia:</hi> ſo as of 35000 valiant men, there returned not twenty perſons into <hi>Poland.</hi> Thoſe few hundreds that yeelded up the City, coming once to plenty of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals, died with meat in their mouthes through meer weakneſs, having not taſted a bit of bread in ſix months before. In which Siege, a loaf of bread ſometime was ſold for a thouſand Robles, which is 500 <hi>l.</hi> Sterling.</p>
            <p>During the time of this cruel Siege, wherein I continued 22 months, being lodged in the Imperial Palace, ſeveral ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170021:17"/>of miſery preſented themſelves to my fight and obſervation, from the beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; as the eating of the fleſh of horſes, dogs, cats, and all ſorts of leather, boyled in ditch-water; which ſerved in ſtead of Tripes. But that which took moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of grief upon my ſpirits, was, to ſee many Ruſſian Ladies nobly deſcended, and brave young Gentlewomen, who not long before ſcorned that the moiſt earth ſhould have touched the ſoles of their feet, were now become miſerable, conſtrained to go bare-footed, and for food to proſtrate themſelves to every mean perſons diſpoſal; yea, when they were diſcarded by ſome, I have ſeen them with tears in their eyes profer their ſervice to others, and all for a miſerable livelihood: which then called to my remembrance this old ſaying, <hi>Pride muſt have a fall:</hi> and, <hi>Hunger will break ſtone-walls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after the famine grew very great, and all women, children, and aged perſons tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of the City, to the Ruſſians, (who received them very courteouſly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery much condoling their miſerable conditions) there followed a very great judgement of God upon the Polonians, (ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inacie and hardneſs of heart) who all bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170021:17"/>by Oath, and receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon it, not to yeeld up the City to the Ruſſians, ſo long as there was a man of them alive: which brought them to that extremity, that they by caſting lots (who ſhould die next, to maintain the reſt alive) did devour one another, from 3000 to 400 perſons. And at the ſurrender of the City, divers Commanders of the Ruſſian Army ſeizing upon ſundry large cheſts, conceiving them to be full of treaſure, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them broken up, found in them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the bodies of men ſlain for food to the living.</p>
            <p>Upon the regaining of this Imperial Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in 1612. forthwith followed the free election of <hi>Mighaylo Theodorowiche,</hi> (of the lineage of <hi>Borice,</hi> that famous Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) by the two National Armies, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of 13000 Horſe and Foot; who was crowned the 5 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1613.</p>
            <p>This young Prince, for a time, walked in the path of that Princely myrrour of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, <hi>Borice;</hi> under whoſe Government, (after a few yeers of trouble) the Nation enjoyed Halcyon days of peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, after the ceſſation of that long in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine War between the Emperors of <hi>Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Swethland,</hi> and his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170021:18"/>ſon <hi>Guſtavus</hi> the late King of <hi>Swethland;</hi> which was accompliſhed, and the Country of <hi>Scythia</hi> reſtored to the Ruſſian, by the mediation of King <hi>James,</hi> and the indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable reſtleſs pains and travel of the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-honorable ſage States-man, Sir <hi>John Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> employed Lord Ambaſſador there, for that work, for the ſpace of three yeers and eight months; who accompliſhed a League offenſive and defenſive between the two Crowns of <hi>Ruſſia</hi> and <hi>Swethland,</hi> in 1617. which is ſince ratified, by the now-Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Olexey Michaylowiche,</hi> and the Queen of <hi>Swethland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This worthy States-man, Sir <hi>John Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> was by King <hi>James</hi> employed upon a ſecond Embaſſie unto the ſaid Emperour of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> in the yeer 1621. being accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſix Gentlemen of quality, (of whom <hi>Robert Kelloway</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> was firſt in degree) and by 60 followers all in a rich Livery; who accompliſhed his Embaſſie with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to the King, and very great honour to himſelf and this Nation. In both which great Embaſſies, I had the honour to be with him, all the time.</p>
            <p>Thus after this peaceable Emperour had rei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned 35 yeers, he died; to whom ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Olexey</hi> his ſon, who being yet of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170021:18"/>tender yeers, and not knowing the great and weighty cauſes and motives inducing his Princely predeceſſors to grant that great Charter of Free-trade unto the Engliſh Company of Merchants thorowout that vaſt Empire, free of Cuſtom, and all other duties, hath (as is ſuppoſed) by the aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of ſome Dutch Reſident there, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived the English of that Charter. But now, I hope, upon better information, and apprehenſion of the conſtant love of the Engliſh to his Majeſtie and that Nation, and their readineſs on all occaſions from time to time to ſerve and ſupply his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors with all neceſſaries, even in the times of their greateſt ſtraits, will be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient motive to him, moſt honorably and freely to reſtore unto the English Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants the ſaid Charter of Free-trade, and will thereby manifeſt his Princely affection to our victorious Chieftain, or <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who hitherto hath been the Lords threſhing-inſtrument of terrour to all the potent and raging enemies of this Nation, both by land and ſea. All which, the Dutch, as well as others, have been made very ſenſible of, and of which they above any others can make a moſt true Narrative, (if they pleaſe) to the glory of God, the honour of his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170021:19"/>Highneſs, and this nation, and to their own correcti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e inſtruction for the future; leſt their inſulting pride draw them down by a ſecond Duke <hi>d'Alva</hi> to the gulf of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and enforce them once again to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title themſelves to our <hi>Caeſar, The poor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed States of the Netherlands,</hi> as they did in the days of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Queen of <hi>England,</hi> who purchaſed thoſe United Provinces from the Spaniard, by the ineſtimable life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blood of more then 100000 Engliſh-men, beſides Scots and Iriſh, and the expence of more then two millions of treaſure: <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be fully ſatisfied by the worth of all the Netherlands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if any ſhall be offended at theſe my foregoing expreſſions touching our preſent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> victorious Chieftain, (or <hi>Caeſar</hi>) I ſhall hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſire them to look back into the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded tranſactions of all the Worthies in former ages, and ſee if they can <hi>(comparatis comparandis)</hi> balance thoſe many ſeveral no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and victorious acts of his, with any of theirs, in the ſcale of Honour, and true Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnanimity, by him accompliſhed, in three famous Kingdoms, <hi>viz. England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and all within the ſpace of 3 or 4 yeers, without the leaſt foil or repulſe at any time by him received from his &amp; this Nation's potent enemies.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170021:19"/>
            <p>Wherein (in my judgment) he ſurpaſſes the Romane <hi>Caeſars,</hi> the furious <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> the valiant <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> Prince of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirath,</hi> the triumphant <hi>Godfrey of Bullein,</hi> and the victorious <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus</hi> King of <hi>Swethland,</hi> who was the terrour of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many.</hi> And as the Lord in raiſing him up, hath thus by him brought home peace to every man's door in theſe three Nations; ſo I deſire and wiſh from my ſoul, that with all due thankfulneſs he and we may return praiſes to his great and glorious Name for thoſe his rich and abundant mercies by this his ſelect inſtrument <hi>(Oliverus)</hi> conferred on us; it being the onely true way for the continuation of his ſhowers of mercies on us; and, in ſtead of kicking againſt the pricks, to reſt ſatiſfied, and wait patiently upon the Lord, and then doubtleſs the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of God will appear: for, <hi>he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, maketh not haſte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For that ſacred Power that hath hitherto by him accompliſhed mighty things for us, will aſſuredly perfect his work, even his own great work; ſo that the enemies of God, and all that hate us, beholding it, ſhall ſtand amazed, &amp; ſhall be enforced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs and ſay, that <hi>it is the Lords doings, and it is marvelous in their eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170021:20"/>
            <p>And when once, according to his ſundry expreſſions at ſeveral times to that effect, he appears mighty in pulling down the ſtrong holds of Satan, and advancing the thrones of Juſtice, Judgment, and Mercy, to the glory of God, the good of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his own eternal praiſe, then ſhall his enemies be abaſhed, and <hi>England</hi>'s ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies confounded; but on him ſhall the mercies of God flouriſh. For, it is Juſtice and Mercy exalts a Nation, and the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration thereof (without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) is the honour of a Nation, and of him that is the Head of the Nation. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thoſe unalterable decrees of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians:</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, that <hi>the throne is eſtabliſhed by juſtice, and upholden by mercy,</hi> Prov. 20.28. For <hi>he that ruleth over men muſt be just,</hi> honourable, and unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in his word and promiſe) <hi>ruling in the fear of God,</hi> 2 Sam. 23.3. <hi>And he ſet judges in the land city by city, and ſaid to the judges, Take heed what ye do for ye judge not for man, but for the Lord, who is preſent with you in the judgment: for there is no iniquity nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons with the Lord, nor taking of gifts.</hi> 2 Chron. 19.5, 6, 7. This undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly was the leſſon which our juſt <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred</hi> King of <hi>England</hi> gave to all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-Judges
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170021:20"/>and Chancellors in his days: and this was the charge of that renowned Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Borice;</hi> and this, I hope, will be the Rule and unalterable Charge of our victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Caeſar:</hi> And in ſo doing, he ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly retain the favour of God, the love of the whole Nation, and make his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies vaniſh like the ſmoke. <hi>And ſo doing, go on and proſper; the Lord ſhall give thee thine hearts deſire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that the Lord in mercy to this Nation would turn the preſent tyrannous deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Norman law of <hi>England</hi> into a law of mercy &amp; preſervation to the people there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; that ſo they might not be thereby, in their eſtates, rights; liberties, and lives, daily ſold, as ſheep are in <hi>Smithfield</hi>-market; and by Bayliffs and Serjeants moſt ſpitefully daily haled like dogs to ſeveral dungeons of miſery, from their families and callings, and cruelly deſtroyed in priſons, their eſtates by piecemeal torn and rent from them for a trifle, and their wives and children enforced to beg their bread: yea, many poor hang'd for ten or twenty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; whilſt thoſe that rob this Nation of their eſtates, liberties, and lives, and that by a Law, eſcape the halter.</p>
            <p>Wherefore my moſt humble and earneſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170021:21"/>ſuit unto his Highneſs the Lords threſhing-inſtrument) 15, That he would be pleaſed to take ſeriouſly to heart the miſery of this Nation, as good <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did who accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their miſery his miſery, their bondage his bondage, their fleſh as his fleſh, and their children as his children: <hi>And lo,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>you ſuffer to be brought into bondage your ſons and your daughters,</hi> cauſing thereby the enemies of God to blaſpheme. <hi>Neh.</hi> 5.5, 9. and the oppreſſed to groan under the burthen. <hi>The</hi> (works and) <hi>words of the wicked are to lie in wait for blood: but the mouth of the upright ſhall deliver the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> Prov. 12.6. And alſo ſeriouſly to conſider the admonition of <hi>Solomon,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>If thou forbear to deliver thoſe that are haled to death,</hi> (or dungeons of death) <hi>and if thou ſayſt, Behold, I knew it not; doth not he that pondereth thy heart, and keeps thy ſoul, know it?</hi> And ſo of the Lords judgement denounced by <hi>Jeremiah</hi> againſt the Rulers of <hi>Judah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Ye have not hearkned unto me, in proclaiming liberty every one to his brother, and every one to his neighbour; nor looſed the bands of wickedneſs, nor undone the heavie burdens, nor let the oppreſſed</hi> (nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved) <hi>go free: Therefore will I proclaim li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty unto you, even to the ſword, to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170021:21"/>plague, and to the famine,</hi> Jer. 34.17.</p>
            <p>And do we not ſee the anger of the Lord kindled againſt us, by troubles abroad, jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies at home, and fears on every ſide? Therefore take away the Cauſe, (which is, Injuſtice, Cruelty, and Oppreſſion) and the Effect will ceaſe aſſuredly. For <hi>when</hi> (in theſe things) <hi>a mans ways pleaſe the Lord, his very enemies ſhall be at peace with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore the Lord, in mercy to his Highneſs and this Nation, be pleaſed to incline his heart to looſe the bands of wickedneſs, (by aboliſhing the <hi>Capias</hi>) and to let the oppreſſed go free; to pull down the thrones of iniquity, and to break every yoke: Then ſhall his light break forth (to the Nation) as the morning, and his health ſhall then ſpring forth ſpeedily: his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous acts ſhall then be his van-guard, and the glory of the Lord (in the power of his might) ſhall be his rere-guard. For bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall he be that conſidereth the cauſe of the poor, (eſpecially thoſe that are of up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right heart) the Lord ſhall deliver him out of his enemies hands, and he ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon the earth; yea, his enemies ſhall be deſtroyed: but he ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſs, and his ſeed after him; if he deſpiſe not the counſel of the poor,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170021:22"/>whoſe truſt is in the Lord; if he cleave not to the generation of cruel men, but eaſe this Nation of this cruel Norman bondage, and deliver the inſlaved for debt out of the ſeveral dens of cruelty in this Land, cauſing ſpeedy juſtice to have its free current without reſpect of perſons, that ſo all that are oppreſſed and defrauded of their eſtates, lands, or goods, may gain ſpeedy reſtitution with damage for falſe impriſonment, or detention of their eſtates unjuſtly.</p>
            <p>All which once effected, will aſſuredly appeaſe the wrath of God againſt theſe Nations, unite the hearts of all this great people to his Highneſs, as the heart of one man, and will enable him to go in and out before this great people in the ſtrength of the Lord, and the power of his might, in peace and much ſafety, maugre all his enemies, and all that ſtrive to diſturb his and this Nations peace. This will aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly bring glory to God, honour to his Highneſs, and tranquillity to the Nation: it will enforce (as in other Countries) ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and plain-dealing from all men and all Petifogging, deceitful, ſubtil, oppreſſive perſons, now ſhrowded under the Norman Law, will vaniſh; and the words <hi>Peace,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170021:22"/>Quietneſs,</hi> and <hi>Induſtry,</hi> will be written o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver every mans door.</p>
            <p>Such noble acts will revive the memory of <hi>Alfred,</hi> that juſt king of <hi>England,</hi> who puniſhed and hanged Four and fourty County-Judges in one yeer, for oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the people by falſe Judgement: and of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, who cauſed Fifteen Gaolers to be hanged in one yeer, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting money from priſoners, and defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them of the King's allowance of 4 <hi>d. per diem:</hi> And of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, who cauſed Two and twenty Projectors, and ſix Aldermen of <hi>London</hi> to be hanged at the then-place of Execution within <hi>London</hi>-walls, and buried under the Gallows; where ſince the Church is built, and the place called <hi>Alderman-bury,</hi> to this day.</p>
            <p>It was the uſual ſaying of that famous and juſt Emperour <hi>Borice, That Prince or Ruler is most happie and ſafe, that liveth least to himſelf, and moſt to the honour of God, and the peoples good over whom God hath placed him; and whoſe legal and juſt power is the bounds of his will: whoſe olive-branch of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſpringeth from his heart, bloometh on his tongue, and beareth fruit in his actions; which will always direct him not to refuſe counſel good cheap, leſt remiſs ſecurity cauſe him to buy repentance too dear.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170021:23"/>
            <p>Thus having (through my real hearty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and well-wiſhes to his Highneſs well-being, and love to my Countries free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, peace, and tranquillity) digreſſed from my intended Hiſtorical Subject: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous not to weary the Reader, but to draw to an end, I do again (in the cloſe) become a moſt humble and earneſt ſuitor to his Higneſs, in the name, and by the mercies of Jeſus Chriſt, to let <hi>judgement run down as water, and juſtice as a mighty ſtream;</hi> that ſo Mercy may embrace him on every ſide, and cauſe him to continue in aſſured love and favour both with God and man, enjoying the good things of this Land in peace, (internal, and external) with abundance of glory to God, and honour to himſelf and poſterity.</p>
            <p>Not giving ear to the feigned words of ſome ſelf-ſeeking perſons, who having a ſhew of godlineſs, (yet deny the power thereof) do (<hi>Babel</hi>-like) endeavour to rear up to themſelves everlaſting tabernacles, and cry out, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, The Temple of the Lord; The Law, the Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Whereas the true Temple of the Lord is this, To amend their covetous ways, and their unjuſt oppreſſive doings, To execute judgement between a man and his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170021:23"/>and not to oppreſs the poor, the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, the fatherleſs, nor the ſtranger, but to let all the oppreſſed &amp; enſlaved go free: Nor to think, by tything Mint and Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, to fulfil the law of God, as thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral hypocrites, the Doctors, Lawyers, Scribes and Phariſees did; againſt whom (in ſtead of a bleſſing) there ſtands upon record for ever ſundry terrible Woes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by him who is King of kings, and Lord of life and glory, and who aſſuredly will, by the ſacred Rule of impartial juſtice, judge them according to their works.</p>
            <p>There is a Word, which is clothed with death; the Lord grant it be not found in the heritage of <hi>Jacob.</hi> Sometimes to abide in the ſhade, produceth more quiet to a poor man, then to have the bright beams of the Princes favour to break forth upon him: for then Malice is forthwith enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, Wrath like a Fury aſſaulteth, and Revenge like a Crocodile (when ſeeming to weep over him) deſtroys him moſt, in his credit, life, and good name; never ceaſing (both by himſelf, and all thoſe by him ſeaſoned for his ends) to traduce and backbite him daily, thereby rendering him odious to the beſt of men.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170021:24"/>
            <p>Like thoſe ſubtil Serpentine generation of men, who by lyes and ſlanders, and by the power of ſome by them then ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned for the work, defrauded me of my right, which by his Highneſs favour was moſt freely conferred on me; and who alſo ſince have notceaſed to traduce, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite, and ſlander me to thoſe in high place and Authority, hoping thereby to make their deeds of darkneſs to reſemble the light and truth, in the fight of his Highneſs and others. But to all ſuch ſhadows of Chriſtians I ſhall ſay but this, That their Conſciences (if they have any) cannot but teſtifie to their faces that they have done me much wrong: <hi>The Lord rebuke them for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this I was told long ſince, that if his Highneſs had not appeared ſo vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly for me in that, and another buſineſs ſince that, I had neither undergone thoſe calumnies and reproaches, nor had my endeavours proved ſo fruitleſs as hitherto they have done to me.</p>
            <p>This duely weighed, it cannot but be poſitively concluded, That although thoſe ſlanderous and reproachful arrows were ſhot at the lowe ſhrub, yet the venome of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170021:24"/>them was intended to hit the tall Cedar, which by his branches of favour was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſhelter the lowe ſhrub.</p>
            <p>For at that very inſtant time, the better to ſet a face of credit upon their ſlanders, and to carry on their deſigne of defeating me of my right, they by their inſtruments divulged it abroad in the City, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Parliament-men, that I had forſwore my ſelf three times in one day before his Highneſs and the Councel, and that they had adjudged me to ſtand in the Pillory at the Exchange. This was related with ſuch a face of truth, as that divers of my friends were happily deceived, in going to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change to be ſpectators of it.</p>
            <p>Whereas the real truth is, that I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver called before his Highneſs nor Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel to ſwear at any time, for any matter, cauſe, or thing whatſoever: for the truth whereof, I humbly appeal to his Highneſs and to the honorable Councel; moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly praying for juſtice on theſe traducers, and ſatisfaction for theſe injuries moſt wrongfully ſuſtained.</p>
            <p>But not reſting in the centre of theſe their calumnies, they or their inſtruments do ſtill perſiſt by under-hand plottings to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170021:25"/>accompliſh my deſtruction, and by raiſing of a lye againſt me, rob me of my lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: and at the ſame time, in a moſt ſecret manner, ſpread a rumour in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that I ſhould conſpire againſt my Lord Protector's life: A thing ſo horrid, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable to my ſoul, and ſo far from the thoughts of my heart, as the Cryſtalline Sphere can poſſibly be in diſtance from the earth.</p>
            <p>And this clearly appeareth, by my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie from the beginning, to the cauſe of God, faithfulneſs to his Highneſs, and ſervices performed for the State.</p>
            <p>The firſt was, my diſcovery of the late King's intention to ſurpriſe <hi>Hull</hi> and <hi>Ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> by private Letters ſent out of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to Sir <hi>Harbottle Grimſton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Vaſſel,</hi> then members of Parliament: by means whereof, the Parliament and Nation were preſerved from the univerſal ruine determined, in 1641.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was, my diſcovery of the firſt Rebellion in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For both which, I never to this day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived one peny, as a recompence or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, from any.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170021:25"/>
            <p>And what my fidelity, and many yeers cruel ſufferings, have been, for Parliament and Army, and in eſpecial to his Highneſs, is well-known to thouſands in the City and Countries, and manifeſted by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Tractates written and printed by me in defence of the Cauſe, and of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs honour; even at that time alſo, when black-mouth'd envious Infamy had open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her mouth wide againſt him: from which I ſhall never vary, nor ceaſe to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate his honour in the way of God: wiſhing from my ſoul, that all men were even as I am; which is ſo far from acting, wiſhing, or thinking any hurt to him or his, as that I ſhall ſpend my life, and be ready to be ſpent for him; yea, although he ſhould ſuffer me to be overwhelmed with ſorrow, penury, and the raging pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of my ſlanderous adverſaries.</p>
            <p>For the real truth of all which, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the ſearcher of all hearts, who knows that I lye not, and to whoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred hand of juſtice and mercy I refer my adverſaries; concluding with <hi>David</hi>'s words: <hi>Plead my cauſe, O Lord, with them that ſtrive with me: Fight thou againſt them that fight againſt me;</hi> and, <hi>From
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170021:26"/>evil and deceitful men, O Lord deliver me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For they that work evil, ſhall be wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up in evil. Slander and reproach proceed from the proud in heart; but vengeance lurketh for them as a lion: yea, Anguiſh ſhall conſume them before they die, and they ſhall be taken in the ſame ſnare.</p>
            <p>The tongue of the hypocrite deſtroyeth his neighbour by lying words; yea, he worketh deceitfully without ceaſing; (I wiſh this Age hath not brought forth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch monſters) who bend their tongues like a bowe for lyes, and take great pains to do wickedly.</p>
            <p>Witneſs the numberleſs number of backbiters, falſe accuſers, Knights of the Poſt, forgers of Deeds, tormentors of poor men and women by frequent vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Arreſts, Impriſonments, and tedious Suits in Law, of Ten, Twenty, Thirty, or Fourty yeers continuance.</p>
            <p>I cannot but with grief of heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that we live in the very laſt of times, wherein Malice lurketh, Revenge rageth, Cruelty ſucketh the vital blood of the poor, Envie ſuffereth not the poor to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170021:26"/>live; Oppreſſion ſtayeth the needy; the poor is deſpiſed of his neighbour, his faithfulneſs contemned, and his ſervices not regarded, (if he be not armed with the ſpirit of boldneſs, impudence, and baſe flattery) as many are, who have thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved beſt, and prevailed moſt, ſince theſe diſtracted times, and have made great gain by the bare profeſſion of Godlineſs, but of true godlineſs ſmall gain to themſelves, (in the practical part thereof.)</p>
            <p>Some ſuch are they, who have troubled me, perplexed me, perſecuted me, defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me, and endeavoured to deſtroy me, by lying words. The Lord in mercy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, and give them hearts to walk more anſwerably to their profeſſion, and preſerve his Highneſs from being decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and deluded by any ſuch Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</p>
            <p>It was the approved wiſdome of that famous Emperour <hi>Borice,</hi> Not to truſt any reconciled Enemy, nor to intruſt them in any place of power, nor to credit any their Blemiſhes and Odiums in ſecret caſt upon any of approved fidelity to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>This Rule produced peace and ſafety
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170021:27"/>to him, but confuſion to his enemies, and to all their <hi>Machavilian</hi> plots and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes againſt him.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, Credulity, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, and favouring of reconciled ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, was the deſtruction of that Heroick Spirit <hi>Demetrius</hi> the Emperour, who by their Flatteries lulling him aſleep in their treacherous Cradle of Security, made thereby his Friends appear to him to be his Foes, and themſelves (that were his mortal Enemies) to be his onely Friend, by his confining of his ear unto them.</p>
            <p>An eminent Example we have for this, in the late King, who upon the compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition between the Spaniſh and French Faction of his Councel, granted the pre-eminence to the Spaniſh Faction, as to <hi>Cant', Arund', Cott', Wind',</hi> and others, by confining his ear ſolely to them; which proved his confuſion. For, the Plot being laid long before, by the Pope and Jeſuites, to make the King of <hi>Spain</hi> UNIVERSAL KING, theſe <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavels</hi> knew no ſurer way to accompliſh this, then in rendering the King odious
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170021:27"/>to the people, by multiplying of Taxes, and countenancing the ſeveral Judges in their corrupt practices. The Biſhops, by the High-Commiſſion-Court, new inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Orders in their Churches, and the Oath <hi>Ex Officio.</hi> Putting the King alſo upon requiring Knighthood-money, Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money, the Foreſts, and others of that nature: being confident, that this would move the people (by them called Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks) to rebel, and ſo cut the throats one of another; and thus the Catholikes might but ſtand by, and laugh at their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and then the King of <hi>Spain</hi> with much facility might of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> gain the poſſeſſion: which done, the <hi>Netherlands</hi> would ſoon follow, and <hi>France</hi> alſo be brought into ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>How far they prevailed in this their helliſh Plot, I appeal to all knowing perſons: and what good the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to this Nation out of evil by them intended, is manifeſt at this day.</p>
            <p>The Lord perfect this his Work of Mercy to us, by granting us the aſſurance
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170021:28"/>of his love and favour in Jeſus Chriſt; which cannot but produce honour to his Highneſs, and peace and happineſs to this Nation: Which is the hearty deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithful friend and ſervant in the Lord,
<hi>J. F.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:170021:28"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>For the help and enabling of all poor op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eatures, that are not able to wage Law, or to undergo the chargeable corrupt practice thereof for recovery of their Rights;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THat his Highneſs would be pleaſed to cauſe a Proclamation or Declaration to be made thorowout the whole Nation, thereby declaring that all Decrees made againſt any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in any Court of Juſtice or Equity, without hearing of the party, or Counſel for him, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the making thereof, being contrary to the Laws and Statutes of this Nation, ſhall become void. And that thoſe Judges that be living, of them which made the ſaid Decrees, ſhall anſwer and pay unto the party damnified there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, his full loſs and damage ſuſtained by reaſon thereof, within certain days to be limited, after Oath made of the demand thereof: and upon failer therein, that then an Extent to iſſue of courſe, without any circuit of Action or Suit at Law againſt the ſaid unjuſt Judge or Judges their eſtates both real and perſonal; and then
<pb facs="tcp:170021:29"/>to pay double damages for their ſaid failer. And that the ſaid Proclamation or Declaration ſhall be a ſufficient warrant to any Sheriffs or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers whatſoever to levie all ſuch money as ſhall appear to be due for the reaſons aforeſaid: any Statute, Law, or Ordinance to the contrary heretofore made, in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And whoſoever hath illegally, in the time of a priſoners reſtraint, intruded and gotten into the poſſeſſion of any of his lands or goods, and received the profits thereof, &amp; converted them unto his or their own uſe, and do ſtill unjuſtly detain them: If any ſuch perſon or perſons do not (after ſo many days limited as aforeſaid) upon demand deliver the poſſeſſion of the ſaid Lands quietly unto the parties ſo wronged, or unto ſuch as he ſhall appoint, with all the profits thereof, and goods by him or them, or any of them, ſo taken away, That then to reſtore four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: and for ſuch as have no eſtates to give ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, may receive corporal puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Law of</hi> England <hi>being a Law of mercy and preſervation, and not as it's now in the practice thereof become a Law of rigour and deſtruction to the people; therefore it is further humbly prayed,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That none may be arreſted nor impriſoned for debt, but that after three ſeveral citations,
<pb facs="tcp:170021:29"/>the debtor not appearing, judgment to paſs, and execution on his eſtate. This will make all men cautious of running into debt, and others wary whom they truſt. Whereby Trade will flouriſh as in <hi>Germany, Holland, Flanders,</hi> &amp; other parts of the world. It will preſerve Gentlemens heirs from being ruined (before they can poſſeſs their eſtates) by Uſurers, Brokers, and Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, as thouſands have been.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That all Cheaters, and ſuch-like, may walk with their noſtrills ſtil, in ſtead of a cropt ear; as in <hi>Germany, Ruſſia,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That none may be put to death for theft, it being conſonant to the law of God.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That all Waſtes and Commons may be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally divided among the poor of each Periſh.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> That all groundage at ſea may be aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, goods imbezeled to be reſtored freely to the owners. In which act of juſtice and mercy, Turks and Pagans ſurpaſs us far at preſent.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> That the Norman power <hi>(ad Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum)</hi> being at a period, therefore all Villanage, Vaſſalage, Fines, and Heriots, to be aboliſhed, together with Court-Leets and Barons.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> All controverſies to be determined by three men in every Hundred &amp; Town-Corporate (and thoſe to be changed yeerly) with freedom of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the Provincial Court, for any act of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice by them paſſed injudgement.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170021:30"/>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> That a Regiſter be kept in every County, for the ſale of lands, leaſes, houſes, and farms; and all private ſales to be accounted illegal.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9.</hi> That the yeerly progreſs of the Prince may now again be founded on its original baſis, as in the days of K. <hi>Alfred, viz.</hi> to ſee juſtice have its free and clear current thorowout the Land without reſpect of perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe nine particulars not varying much from the Armies Petition of</hi> July <hi>14. 1649. will I hope finde a favourable acceptation from him, on whom the Lord hath now conferred the power of all at preſent, and hath I hope ſet him over us for good, and not for evil; though the Royal party back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite him, and ſpeak evil of him daily, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and plotting his deſtruction, and the deſtruction of all that love him, and adhere unto him. But that ſacred mighty power which hitherto hath kept him ſafe, will ſtill preſerve him, cauſing his mercies to flouriſh on him, maugre all thoſe that hate him, If he do the work of the Lord thorowly and faithfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
